Guide to the Robert E. and Gladys Wilson Bundy Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Robert E. and Gladys Wilson Bundy Papers
1890-1983
RG 141
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(6 boxes)
Letters, writings, and printed material document the missionary work of the Bundys as well as social and political events in China from 1923 to 1927. The 1926 siege of Wuchang is particularly well documented. Robert and Gladys Bundy were American Episcopal missionaries at Boone University, Wuchang, China from 1923 to 1927, and at St. Paul's University, Tokyo, Japan from 1927 to 1929.
Bundy, Robert E.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul and Catharine Ward.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Bundy was born in Bethel, Vermont. Robert and Gladys, both graduates of Middlebury College, were married in 1917. Prior to their misisonary work, Gladys taught in Barre, VT and in Puerto Rico and Robert was in business in Rochester, Vermont. Their daughter, Dorris, was adopted during their 1925-1926 furlough. Following their service in China and Japan, they returned to live in Bethel.
The Bundys served under the American Church Mission (Episcopal) at Boone University, Wuchang, China from 1923 to 1927 and at St. Paul's University, Ikebukuro, Tokyo, Japan from October 1927 to 1929.
Scope and Contents
Early correspondence of Gladys Bundy (approx. 100 letters) consists mostly of letters to "family" (actually a courtesy family, the Pinkhams, with whom she had resided). These letters discuss political conditions around Wuchang as well as their daily life at Boone University, which was part of a four-way merger of mission schools forming Central China University in 1924. Riots in Wuchang forced the closing of Boone Middle School in June of 1925.
Upon their return to China in September of 1926, after a furlough, Gladys and Dorris went to Kuling and Robert headed for Wuchang but was prevented from getting beyond Hankow because the siege of Wuchang by southern troops had begun on September 1. His letters to Gladys (Sep 3-Oct 7) describe the siege, discussing the role of missionaries like Dr. Wakefield, Bishop Gilman, and Mr. Kean in negotiations and Bundy's own involvement in getting supplies to the city and evacuating the inhabitants. Newspaper accounts, reports by other missionaries, and photographs also provide day by day documentation of this episode.
The Bundys were reunited in Wuchang on October 10th, 1926 and Gladys' letters describe the student attitudes, damage to the city, and new rules and regulations under southern rule. Included in Robert's correspondence is his statement supporting neutrality on the part of foreign missionaires in China's civil wars. (1926 Dec 23)
The remainder of the papers consists of scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, station reports, and other printed material about the political, economic, and social conditions in China from 1923-1937, and other miscellaneous items. A good portion of the material in the collection is directly related to the siege of Wuchang. There is only one letter from the Bundys' years in Tokyo, 1927-1929 in the original Correspondence series, but more in the Addendum that was added in 2001. The Addendum also includes writings and notes of Robert Bundy, journals, and personal items and memorabilia.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1922-1983
II. Writings, 1925, 1927, 1960
III. Collected Material, 1909-1931
IV. Addendum, 1924-1981
Missions -- China; Wuchang (Hubei Sheng, China) -- Church history; Bundy, Gladys Wilson; Bundy, Robert E.; Episcopal Church -- Missions -- China
- Correspondence, 1922-1983; Series I
  - Correspondence with donors of the papers, Catharine and Paul L. Ward, including article re. Bundys, 1967, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of Gladys Bundy, 1924-1926 (Box 1, Folder 2-10)
  - Correspondence of Robert Bundy, 1922-1928 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
- Writings, 1925, 1927, 1960; Series II
  - Travel diary of Gladys Bundy, recording journey to U.S. on furlough, 1925 Jun- Jul (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Article by Robert Bundy: "The Way to Fight Bolshevism", 1927 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Article by Robert Bundy: "Four Months Under Communism", ca. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Collected Material, 1909-1931; Series III
  - Photographs
    - Re. siege of Wuchang, 1926 Sep 3 - Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Printed material
    - Early Chinese newspaper published in Hong Kong, "Weixin ribao" ("Reform Daily");Book on teaching the Chinese language, by Paul Kranz, 1890,1909 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - China Tomorrow, 1929 Feb 20 - May 25 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous printed material: reprints, station reports, strike broadsides, 1924-1928 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Newsclippings - general, 1926 Oct - 1927 Feb (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Newsclippings re. Wuhan flood (from The North China Herald, 1931 Aug 11-25 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbooks
    - "China News", 1927 Aug (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Last days of Reds in Wuhan" (clippings from Hankow Herald and Japan Advertiser, 1927 Jun 8 - Jul 31 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "The Nanking Affair/ Communism in Central China", 1927 Feb - May (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Wuchang siege accounts
    - "Wuchang siege letters" by Theodore Bliss, 1926 Sep 4 - Oct 10 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Diary of E. Mildred Buchanan...", 1926 Aug 26 - Oct 10 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Account of the First Ten Days" by Paul Wakefield, 1926 Sep 1 - 11 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Addendum, 1924-1981; Series IV
  - Correspondence
    - Robert Bundy (RB) to Gladys Bundy (GB), 1925 Oct-1926 May (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
    - GB to family, from Japan, 1928 Jan-Jul (Box 3, Folder 32-34)
    - GB to Mrs. Pinkham, from Japan, 1928 Aug-1930 Aug (Box 3, Folder 35-42)
    - GB/ RB corres. to/from others, incl. P. Utsonomiya, Paul Ward, Mother Wilson, Arthur Lichtenberger, Logan Roots, Miss Armbruster, 1927-1959 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - John Coe to RB, 1925 Oct-1934 Dec (Box 4, Folder 44-46)
    - Paul Wakefield to RB, 1927 May-Dec (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - F. C. Brown, E. A. Shepherd, P. Utsonomiya, 1927 Sep-1928 Dec (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Corres. of others: Mary Coe, D. Bergamini, H. Kao, 1926-1939 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Writings of Robert Bundy
    - Poem (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - "The Siege of Wuchang", 1926 Sep (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - "Wakefield of Wuchang" (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Speech given to Laymen's Club - Boone Univ., 1924 Nov (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - "Just Visiting" by Old "We" - newspaper column - VT (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - "Can the Truth Catch Up with the Lie?" (re. Sen. McCarthy vs. Lattimore) (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Thesis: "Some traces of the influence of the four books of the Chinese classics on the writings of Ralph Waldo Emerson" (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Drafts. re. Emerson; Fuji no ya ma (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Writings of others
    - Paul Ward: conversations with John Coe, 1981 Mar (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Paul Wakefield: Siege of Wuchang, 1926 Sep (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Unidentified: re. Emperor's coronation (Box 4, Folder 59a)
  - Journals
    - RB: Japan, 1929 May (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - RB: Travels, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - RB: Vermont, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - GB: Re. Dorris (daughter), 1927 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Notes
    - College lecture notes, 1926-1929 (Box 4, Folder 64-68)
    - Booklist (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Notes re. American Church Mission, Hankow, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Personal Items and Memorabilia
    - Biographical documentation; Misc. programs, etc. (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Photographs; newspaper clipping re. 50th anniversary of GB/ RB (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - Maps, tourist notes (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - Collected material re. Horace, re. folklore and traditions (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Japanese language study books (Box 6, Folder 75-78)